<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble essay toward the settlement of peace and truth in the church, as a certain foundation of lasting union by Sir Edward Harley.</title>
            <author>Harley, Edward, Sir, 1624-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11056</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11994869</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11994869</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52075</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52075)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 815:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble essay toward the settlement of peace and truth in the church, as a certain foundation of lasting union by Sir Edward Harley.</title>
                  <author>Harley, Edward, Sir, 1624-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for N. Simmons ... and T. Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681 .</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52075:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52075:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Humble Eſſay TOWARD The Settlement of <hi>Peace and Truth</hi> IN THE CHURCH, As a Certain Foundation OF Laſting Union.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>The Workman made it therefore it is not God.</hi> 
               <bibl>Hoſ. 8.6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Nec enim Fas eſt Cultorem Dei a Dei Cultore Violari.</hi> 
               <bibl>Lactantius <hi>Lib. de Ira Dei,</hi> cap. 14.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>N. Simmons</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> and <hi>T. Simmons</hi> in <hi>Ludgate</hi>-ſtreet. 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:52075:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52075:2"/>
            <head>AN Humble Eſſay Toward the ſettlement of Peace and Truth in the Church, as a certain Foundation of laſting Union.</head>
            <p>THE Dignity of Mankind above the ſenſual Brutes conſiſts ſpecially in the hope of Eternal Happineſs, the Direction and ground of which hope is Religion. All Religions that ever were embraced, pretended Authority from Divine Revelation, and the Command of God: the Truth and Certainty of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, hath alone this excellency, to be a firm and evident ground of hope of Eternal, Happineſs. For Chriſtian Religion by undeniable proof is Authorized by the Command and Inſtitution of God; and in the Rules and Practice is both agreeable to the Simplicity, Purity, Righteouſneſs of the Divine Majeſty the Object, and to the Rational Being of Man the Subject of Religion. The univerſal Practice of all Ages and Countries acknowledgeth the neceſſity of Religion. But Religion is not an Opinion Fanſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſuggeſted, or cunningly deviſed, or powerfully Impoſed, all which can only erect a private or publick Superſtition; which is no more Religion then that Creature is a Man which in its odious reſemblance is the reproach of Man, and therefore the more contemptible: Religion comes from a deeper root and higher cauſe. It is connatural with every Rational Being
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52075:3"/> upon which is indelibly Engraven the Fear, Truſt, and Love of the Power, Truth, and Goodneſs of God. The Blurring theſe Impreſſions cannot be attempted without eſſaſing the Characters of Human Intelligence, and ſinking Man into the loweſt form of Beaſts. Religion is the firſt born of Truth, and as the Oppoſition to Truth is either from a downright Lie; or a veriſimilar Semblance, ſo Religion is either affronted by Atheiſm, or abuſed by Superſtition.</p>
            <p>An Atheiſt properly ſo called, was hardly if ever found, the ſad Pretenders, who have told their miſerable Wiſhes that that there were no God, have been the feweſt in Number, and the weakeſt in Argument of any ſort of Fools ever appeared to diſgrace Mankind. There have been more Idiots and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks then ever there were Atheiſts; and <hi>Bedlam</hi> it ſelf without expecting a lucid Interval can afford as rational Diſcourſes as <hi>Democritus</hi> and <hi>Epicurus</hi> with all their chance Medleys of <hi>Motes</hi> or <hi>Attems.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Atheiſtical Propoſitions are equally unworthy and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of Human Excellence. The Glory of Man peculiar to him, of all material Beings, is that he is not only by unknown Inſtinct, ledd to the end of his Being, but he knows the reaſon of that End for which he was made; and is capable to enjoy the felicity of that Knowledge. We perceive by the Structure and Formation of thoſe Beings, with whom we converſe, what is their uſe and value. The ſhape of the Laborious Ox, and generous Horſe prompt their ſervice and end: No leſs evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent are the indications of Human compoſition. That Man is made in the Image of God, and that his ultimate End and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity is to glorifie and enjoy God for ever, is no remote No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Speculation; it is a truth touches every ſence, and when not clouded by malitious or ſtupid inadvertance draws conviction from every Member,</p>
            <p>The profane contemners of Religion, yet aſſert a uſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per End for everBeing, and all its parts. Permit then the Atheiſt the tryal by his beloved ſence. Let him tell for what End and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52075:3"/> Reaſon of all viſible Beings Man only is formed to kneel upon his knees, and ſupport his Body erect, to lift up his Hands, to lift up his Eyes. Was Nature wiſe in all other, and fooliſh only in the conſtruction of parts to theſe Poſtures without uſe? No, Nature (which is nothing elſe then the will of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty in the Order of the Creatures) formed the Body to thoſe Poſtures for that excellent End of Divine Worſhip. The bended knees teſtifie humble Devotion to the great Creator, from ſence both of the Suplicants mean Original, and infinite diſtance below the Heavenly Majeſty. The ſtretched out Hands evidence as the inability of the Petitioner to help him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſo the earneſt deſires of Divine Aſſiſtance; the up lifted Eyes ſignifie the hope and truſt, and engage the Love of Mind and Heart upon God Almighty, who only can be our neceſſary and all-ſufficent Good. This is a truth ſo undeniable that ſhould ten thouſand Perſons of ſo many different Nations and Languages fortuitouſly meet; if any of that Aſſembly (though every one a ſtranger to all the reſt) kneel, ſtretch out his hands, and lift up his eyes, all preſent would conclude that Perſon by theſe Geſtures performed Adoration to God.</p>
            <p>There is not any in his right Wits can immagine thoſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Devotion either the effect of vain Fear, or the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations of Politick contrivance, for every Rational Mind, muſt be conſcious of the ſame awful Reverence and intire Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, therefore with moſt freedom Addreſſeth to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of Religions Worſhip when Human help can leaſt ſuccour, and Human Fear can leaſt awe. It is then moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd that the Innumerable ſober Inhabitants of the World ſhould be fooled and ſcoffed out of their preſent and future feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city by a few profane <hi>Attoms</hi> bred in the ſhallow confines of Wit and folly.</p>
            <p>Well matter it ſelf (the Epicurian Idol) hath conviction enough to baffle an Atheiſt; but paſſing through this Houſe of Clay, if we converſe with what is within; that which prompts the Tongue, and acts the Eye, Hand and Foot; that which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52075:4"/> thinks and rules, it will appear there is a Conſcience of Good and Evil, of Juſtice and Injuſtice always Witneſſing there is a God. This is no precarious conceit, every Man ſometime or other feels within himſelf the powerful accuſation or acquital of Conſcience. This is the Verdict in every Mans breſt which waits upon the Tribunal of God. For it is ſilly as well as profane, to pretend Reverence to God only for the Excellence of his Beeing, without the fear of his Juſtice. The Juſtice of God is the ſecurity of the World without it. Human Society cannot ſafely ſubſiſt. Only the fear of God can rule the Heart, and oblige Conſcience, without which there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be either Order or Relation, Commerce or Propriety. The whole World being continually liable to the aſſaults of Fraud or Violence, untill true Religion give Security and Peace.</p>
            <p>Superſtition is indeed the Apologie of Irreligion, by which back Door Atheiſm ſneaks into the World. For Superſtition having cankered the Mind with unworthy conceptions of God; Atheiſm preſumes to enrage it ſelf againſt the Notion of the Supreme Beeing, it miſconceives and would not Obey and Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Superſtition deveſts the Deity of true Majeſty, and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dares to give it ſelf Laws of good and Evil, of Holy and Profane, and ſo inſtead of worſhiping God, Conſecrates as it were an Idol. God is the only Object of Worſhip, and the only Law-giver of the Rules and Rites,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 33.22.</note> of the Materials and Circumſtances of Religion, whatever Creatures invades this Prerogative of Heaven, though under the moſt Devout and Humble pretence, doth thereby expoſe the God-head, and provokes the ſenſualiſt to deny or contemn that Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſees uſurped upon and dethroned.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Superſtition.</note> Superſtition is vain and ignorant Devotion directed either to a falſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject or to a Right Object in a falſe manner. When directed to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52075:4"/> a falſe Object it is a breach of the firſt and great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me.</hi> In the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to this Commandment is fixed the Foundation of all Religion.<note place="margin">Non poteſt igitur noc Religio a ſapientia ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, nec ſapientia a Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; cerni: quiaidem De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſt, qui &amp; intelligi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet quod eſt ſapientiae &amp;. Hono rari quod eſt Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. Lactant <hi>Lib. 4.</hi> de ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Sap, <hi>P. 356.</hi>
               </note> For as there is no Wiſdom without Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo without Wiſdom there cannot be Religion. The property of Wiſdom being to direct the way to Happineſs, and of Religion to give intereſt in and obligation unto what is perfectly true and good which is only to be found in the Divine Unity. Whatever is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and multiplied muſt neceſſarily forſake the perfection of Unity: And can no more Anſwer the end of Devotion, then can in the Firmament a <hi>Parelius,</hi> or <hi>Mock-Sun</hi> ſhed forth the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of Light, Warmth, and Growth which continually beam from the real Sun.</p>
            <p>An Idol is nothing in the World, that is,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4.</note> no ſuch thing as the Superſtitious ſuppoſe or Eſteem. It cannot do Good or Hurt; or Reward or Puniſh. He that comes to God muſt believe that he is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</note> and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek Him. All we can underſtand of a falſe God, is to know in what Age and Countrey, and by what Artifice the Idol was Conſecrated: And the higheſt Inquiry can only find out that,<note place="margin">Qui ſingit ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cros auro vel mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more unltus, non facit ille Deo. qui rogat ille facit. <hi>Mart.</hi>
               </note> neither the Painter nor the Statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, nor yet the Conſecration can effect this Apotheoſis, 'tis only the deceived Heart makes what he Worſhips to be his God. What a wretched Deity is that which hath no ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but in the deluded fanſie of Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that can at will and pleaſure profane or deſtroy the adored Shrine.</p>
            <p>Knowledge begets Religion, therefore in Holy Scripture, the Profane and the Idolaters are ſaid not to know God, as is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52075:5"/> cheifly charged upon the Prieſts <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.12.</note> and King <hi>Manaſſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 33.13.</note> Ignorance is the Mother of Superſtition it cannot be of true Devotion This is true likewiſe in the other branch of Superſtition, when Worſhip is directed to a right Object in a falſe manner; which is a breach of the ſecond Commandment and incurs the Wrath of God, who is a Jealous God, that will certainly viſit the iniquity of Illegitimate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commanded Worſhip.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> teaches that no Religion is in that place whereſoever any Image is.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> againſt Peril of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> Second Part.</note> This is a Quotation out of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius</hi> who fully gives the Reaſon,<note place="margin">Religio nulla eſt ubicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum eſt—</note> Becauſe God the Object of Worſhip muſt be greater then Man,<note place="margin">Non Religio in Simulacris ſed mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Religionis, <hi>Lact.</hi> de Orig. <hi>&amp;c. Lib. 2. P. 229.</hi>
               </note> and Religion the manner of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip muſt be Divine that is from Heaven.</p>
            <p>Therefore whatſoever Object or Medium of Worſhip is invented or contrived upon the Earth can only have a Mimick Semblance of Religion, but is not Religion.</p>
            <p>The antient Champions of Chriſtianity moſt rationally convinced the Vanity of Heatheniſh ſuperſtition, becauſe their Idols, which were the Mediums of Worſhip, were continually ſubject to the diſpoſition of thoſe that Worſhiped them, which implies the groſſeſt contradiction, <hi>viz.</hi> That Man ſhould make God after his Image. This is that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge condemned by <hi>Minutius Faelix,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Min. Fael.</hi> P. <hi>46.</hi> Sacrilegij enim vel maximi inſtar eſt, Humi quaererequod in ſublimj debesin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire—</note> that ſeeks in the duſt for what can only be found come from above. 'Tis that, like the Witch of <hi>Endor</hi> makes Gods aſcend out of the Earth; ſhe and the unhappy King employed her, were evident Types of what befalls all that forſake the lively Oracles of Divine Truth. A grave <hi>Spectrum</hi> in <hi>Samuels</hi> Mantle may promote the Deceit, but ſtill it is not any thing Divine or Heavenly. Such pretended gods are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52075:5"/> indeed; they cannot make any Holy or Happy;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jon.</hi> 2.8.</note> they can only terrifie and torment when they are Executioners of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine vengeance upon thoſe forſake Mercy by following lying Vanities.</p>
            <p>Such alſo is the Religion that teaches any Medium or way of Worſhip not commanded by God;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23.</note> it may have the ſhew of Wiſdom, but it comes not from above, therefore Saint <hi>James</hi> ſaith it is Earthly, Senſual,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 3.15.</note> Deviliſh. It holds not the Head <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> to whom is given all power in Heaven and in Earth. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the only Saviour, and the only Lawgiver of his Church. He is the only Mediator both of Reconciliation and of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. He only hath Power to Authoriſe the Inſtitutions of Worſhip, and in him only is the promiſe of acceptance. All Religion in every part of it being Conſecrated to us in the Blood of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> So that whatſoever Worſhip is not derived from our Lords Inſtitution,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23.</note> hath neither Command nor Promiſe, therefore is not of Faith, and whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin.</p>
            <p>There may be coſtly Oblations, ſtrict Regularities, clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Devotions, pompous Services in the Worſhip of God, but if uncommanded they fall under that ſevere Animadverſion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath required this at your Hand, in vain do you Worſhip me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.9.</note> Such ſervice is no better then the <hi>Athenian</hi> Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act</hi> 17.22.</note> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls too Superſtitious, an ignorant <hi>Worſhip</hi> of an unknown God.</p>
            <p>We know 'tis equally Treaſon to ſerve a Uſurper, and to Uſurp the Regalities of the Lawful Prince by forging new Standards of Commerce or Charters of Grace, or Laws of Allegiance. It is ſo in Religion <hi>Crimen laſae Divinae Majeſtatis.</hi> To apply any peculiar Act of Worſhip to a Creature, or to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52075:6"/> Inſtitute any Act of Worſhip to God. It is a Principal of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reaſon to Worſhip God only according to his own appointment.<note place="margin">Aug. de Conſen— <hi>Evan.</hi> Lib. <hi>1. c. 18.</hi> —quia ſi alio mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do cum cohere vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, quam ſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendum ipſe dixiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet non ut<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illum Colerent, ſed quod ipſi finxiſſent—<hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.7.</note> For Worſhip not comanded by God, is not Worſhip to God but to Humane Imagination.</p>
            <p>Upon this account the Prophets denounce Judgments upon the <hi>Iſralites</hi> for Blaſpheming God upon the Hills; that is in the high Places where God was Worſhiped in a manner not commanded by God. Therefore it remains a blemiſh upon the good Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See this fully evinced by Mr, <hi>Mede</hi> in his <hi>Com.</hi> upon <hi>Apoc</hi> c. 13. <hi>P.</hi> 624, 625.</note> who aboliſhed the falſe gods, notwithſtanding, permitted ſuperſtitious Worſhip in the high Places to the true God. The <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo tells the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> that the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi> Worſhipped they knew not what.<note place="margin">—2 <hi>King.</hi> 15.4.35. 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 33.17.</note> Not becauſe they worſhipped a falſe God, that was not their Crime; but becauſe they ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God by a Worſhip invented by Man and not appointed by God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.22.</note> 'twas therefore meer Superſtition which could not bring to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the bleſſed of End of true Religion. Superſtition is fitly called a colloguing with God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.14.</note> conſequently the acceptance muſt be as diverſe from that of Religion, as flattery is from friendſhip. For they only are the friends of <hi>Chriſt</hi> that keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</p>
            <p>Religion is the rule of true Wiſdom to bring Mankind to Eternal Happineſs,<note place="margin">Religion.</note> by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting all his affections and actions to their proper Object ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will and command of God. God <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 45.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.26, 27.</note> who made the World of nothing created it not in vain. He formed it to be inhabited; and made of one Blood all Nations of Men, for to dwell on all the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52075:6"/> Face of the Earth, that they ſhould ſeek the Lord. Not as though he needed any thing, ſeeing he giveth to all life, and breath, and all things, Neither is he worſhipped with Mens, hands, nor dwells in Temples made with hands. It is equally impoſſible for Man to be happy without Religious dependance upon his Creator. And for the Worſhip or Service of any Created Being to be neceſſary unto God.</p>
            <p>The whole world was made an Harmonious Scheme; every Being from the leaſt and loweſt, to the greateſt and higheſt, chiming into the Conſort, whereof Man was the chief Muſitian,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29.</note> Man was made upright in a likeneſs of conformity to his Creator. His mind, will, and affections repleniſhed with Divine knowledg, Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, by which he was capacitated to exerciſe the Dominion beſtowed upon him by God, over all the Living Inhabitants of the Air, Earth and Water. Man therefore is juſtly defined to be a Rational Religious Creature, therein conſiſting the formal ultimate difference from a Brute, and the higheſt character of his Nature.</p>
            <p>The Excellency of true Religion to be ſuch as before repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, will appear in all the due acceptations thereof; by which alſo will be manifeſted the vanity and miſchief of all falſe Religions;<note place="margin">Rectum eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex ſui &amp; obliqui.</note> for Truth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the Rule and Indication both of it ſelf and of what is falſe.</p>
            <p>God who ſubjected all Creatures to Man bound Man to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by the Law of Religion. This was the Covenant of Life, God vouchſafed to man as ſoon as Created, which our Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> rehearſed to the Scribe in the Goſpel—<hi>Thou ſhalt Love the Lord thy God with all thy Soul and Mind, and Heart, and ſtrength; and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf; do this and thou ſhalt live.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.28.</note> This is the perfect Rule of true Wiſdom, the way to real Happineſs; when the Soul and Mind, the underſtanding and Judgment
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52075:7"/> know God as the only Infinite All-ſufficient Good, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Creator, Ruler, and Preſerver of all Beings, thence concludes there can be no happineſs, but in conformity to the will, and enjoyment of the favour of God; accordingly the whole Heart, Will, and Affections, Fear, Truſt, Hope, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in God; and the ſtrength of all the Powers both intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual and animal Serve, Obey, and Prays His Sovereign Lord in whom he lives, moves, and hath his Being. This is <hi>vita frui,</hi> To live indeed.</p>
            <p>As the Eternal Power of the invinſible Godhead is clearly ſeen by the Creation of the World, ſo all the Creatures we ſee have ſuch evident Signatures of the Divine Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs as exact a behaviour; converſe, and enjoyment, according to the Law of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Love; for love is the fulfilling, and Luſt is the tranſgreſſion of the Law.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.9, 10.</note> Therefore he loves not God who loves not Himſelf and his Neighbour in conformity to the Image of God in which Man was made Holy and Upright.</p>
            <p>How Pleaſant, and Safe, and Happy would Life be, if every one did to another, only what he would receive from another; if every one were ſincerely loved by every one!</p>
            <p>This is Natural Religion, for he only that doeth Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is Righteous, as God is Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 3.7.</note> This was the felicity of innocent Man before his Heart was venomed with Luſt and Vanity. And even now the work of this Divine Law is Written in all Mens Hearts to which their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bear Witneſs.</p>
            <p>The Concluſion or ſumm of the whole matter of Religion is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>Fear God and keep his Commandments, This is the whole Duty of Man.</hi> Therefore the ſecond part of Religion, called Inſtituted, is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in neceſſarily compriſed, and from thence derives Evidence of Authority and Obligation, being given before the fall, to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52075:7"/> eſtabliſh and direct natural Religion, and ſince the fall to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply its defects. This part of Religion is fitly called ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, or Revealed, and is known not by Reaſon, but by Faith For though it be the higheſt Reaſon to believe the Word of God which is the only ground of Faith, yet Faith is above Reaſon, repreſenting things not ſeen by Reaſon, and eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Divine Objects more certainly then any Method of Reaſon can demonſtrate <hi>viz.</hi> by the infallible word of God.</p>
            <p>Inſtituted Religion is the Rule of Divine Worſhip both Moral and Ceremonial, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by God.<note place="margin">Inſtituted Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Prayer by which the Heart powers out it ſelf to God, by which the Soul aſcends to God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62, 8.</note> is only ſuch when animated with the Priviledge and Authority of Gods Word.</p>
            <p>For only God can teach how he pleaſeth to be prayed unto and worſhipped.<note place="margin">Solus Deus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere poteſt ut ſe velet orari.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is the Word of God that teaches we ſhall not be heard for our much ſpeaking;<note place="margin">Tertul. <hi>de O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi> c. 9.</note> that we muſt not uſe vain Repetion, as if prayers like <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bricks, were to be delivered by Tale,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.7.</note> or there were Efficacy and Intereſt in a Phraſeologie of Devotion.</p>
            <p>All Fleſh is guilty and ſilent before God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.23.</note> until the word of promiſe opens the lips,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.</note> and teaches the Heart how to pray. And this, <note place="margin">Tertul. p. 6.60. <hi>ſine Monitore quia depectore Oramus.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> was the Practice of Primitive Chriſtianity. It is the Scripture that aſſures <hi>whoever calls on the Name of the Lord,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.13, 14.</note> ſhall be ſaved;</hi> But it alſo ſaith, <hi>How ſhall they call on him whom they have not believed? and how ſhall they believe in him of whom they have not heard? For Faith (without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God)</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</note> comes by hearing, and hearing by the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52075:8"/> word of God, which we cannot hear but by Preaching, the great and ſtanding Ordinance of the Church in all Ages and Diſpenſations,</p>
            <p>In Paradiſe God Preached to <hi>Adam</hi> how he would be Obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, particularly in keeping the Sabbath, in not eating the Tree of Knowledge.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude</hi> 14. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> were Preachers to the Old World before the Flood. And every Age ſince hath enjoyed wherever was a Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.20.</note> the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Promiſe that though God gave the bread of Adverſity, and the Water of Affliction; yet their Eyes and Ears were not deprived of Teachers.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.3.</note> For both the Law and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel inſtruct this Fundamental Leſſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.4.</note> That by the word of God, Man lives more neceſſarily then by Bread. Obedience thereto giving the Warrant and Value to all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious performances; without it all Devotions, though never ſo exactly obſerved,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 5.25.</note> being by God Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Rejected.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7.2.</note> As the Holy Ghoſt by <hi>Stephen</hi> teſtifies againſt the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſequently in all Ages and Places as Preaching hath been either ſlighted or eſteemed, ſo hath Religion it ſelf declined or flouriſhed. How famous were the Churches of <hi>Greece, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Afric,</hi> when <hi>Chriſoſtome, Auſtine,</hi> and other ſuch excellent Biſhops were their Preachers! But when due Preaching was neglected, Ritual Idolatrous Superſtition by degrees fretted and cankerd out the Truth and Power of Chriſtian Religion at laſt (after long Contempt of Divine long-ſuffering which ſhould have led to Repentance) ſadly expoſed thoſe Churches to Ruine and deſolation by the Miſcreant Superſtition of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metaniſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Latine</hi> Churches have been as miſerably ſhipwracked by the Idolatrous Superſtition and Tyrany of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> For not content with the abſolute Simplicity and Spirituality of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52075:8"/> Chriſtian Religion; Pompus Liturgies of Devotion were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented. Upon which Foundation by degrees was reard the whole Tower of Antichriſtian Babel. The Sacrifice of the Maſs, and all other <hi>Popiſh</hi> Idolatries to Saints and Angels ſprang from this Original, to wit, The enjoyning and requiring a Superſtitious Formulary of Words compoſed by Men as a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Liturgy of Divine Service. This Uſurpation upon the Divine Prerogative (whoſe alone it is to give Laws of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) firſt confers upon a ſet of impoſed Words greater Intereſt and Efficaſie of Devotion as more the Prayers of the Church, then any other Supplications though compoſed of expreſs Scripture Phraſes, uttered by the ſame Miniſter, and offered up by the ſame Congregation at the ſame time. This boldneſs once aſſumed Additions were facile; and then without fear of the Lord of the Church, or regard to the Peace of the Church, under the plauſible Name of Eccleſiaſtick Uniformity, this Mechanick or Artificial Religion is enjoyned as the neceſſary Sum of Church Devotion. Hence iſſued thoſe Iliads of Miſchief, for ſo many Ages have Corrupted and Deſtroyed the Church. And wherever ſuch Opinion obtains, there is a Gap opend for the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Idolatry and Tyranny to be re-eſtabliſhed <hi>Jure poſt Liminij.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is but ſuitable to irreligious profane Mouths to ſcoff at Praying by the Spirit; alas poor Creatures they ſeldom name their Maker but to Blaſpheme Him! But any that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> the Clergy of God, they are Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors to <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehas</hi> who knew not God, and have no part nor lot in Him, if they reproach and perſecute thoſe that pray, as did the Glorious Company of the Apoſtles, the Noble Army of Martyrs, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church through out all the World in Primirive Chriſtianity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertul.</hi> p. 6. <hi>ſine monitore quia de pectore.</hi>
               </note> that is, without Bead, Book, or Formulary from the Heart by the Spirit, who helps our infirmities,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 8.26.</note> for we know not what we ſhould pray for as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52075:9"/> we ought. God alone (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith) can teach how he will be prayed unto; and for that end gives us his Holy Spirit.<note place="margin">Tertul. <hi>Lib de Orat.</hi> c. 9.</note> The Divine Form commonly called the Lords Prayer is Doctrinal,<note place="margin">Deus ſolus doce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re potuit ut ſe vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Orari—</note> and the moſt excellent Summary of Prayer, but not always neceſſary to be uſed;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertull.</hi> ibid Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Proſpector humanarum neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſeorſum poſt tradictam orandi diſciplinam Petite Inquit Jus eſt ſuperſtruendi Extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecus petitiones—</note> every Chriſtian hath right to ask in the Name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> for whatſoever is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the will of God; and for Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the Church. 'Tis the Miniſterial Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in Preaching to ſpeak as the Oracles of God, and also to be the Mouth of the People to God in all Prayer and Supplication in the Spirit,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18. &amp; 4.8.12.</note> by which <hi>Chriſt</hi> gives gifts to Men for the work of the Ministry.</p>
            <p>In contradiction to this reaſonable Service in Spirit and Truth which only is acceptable to God, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath turned Prayer into a meer Rote or Charm of unintelligible Words. No wonder then that they have alſo introduced a Ritual of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Religion, for the moſt part a medley of <hi>Judaiſm</hi> and <hi>Hetheaniſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Religious Ceremonies are Acts of Divine Worſhip,<note place="margin">Religious Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> expreſly Inſtituted by God, and to be continued or altered, enforced or abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed only by the command of God. In Holy Scripture the ſame word is for Ceremonies, Precepts, Mandates, Statutes, Judgments, Ordinances of Worſhip, which appeareth by comparing <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.15, 16, <hi>Numb.</hi> 9, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.1.10. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6. and many other Scriptures.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:52075:9"/>
            <p>The Ceremonial Law began imediately upon the Promiſe of Mercy to loſt Man, by God's Inſtitution of Sacrifice, and other Ceremonial Rites vouchſafed as Subſidiary Reliefs and Aſſiſtances to the weakneſs and frailty of Faith in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of a Saviour and Redeemer.</p>
            <p>The Sacrifice Offered by <hi>Abel</hi> could not have been by Faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4.</note> conſequently not acceptable, had there not been an expreſs word of Command and Promiſe from God to be the Object of Faith.</p>
            <p>The difference of Meats clean and unclean was obſerved before the Flood.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.2.</note> After the Flood at ſundry times, and in divers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners it pleaſed the Wiſdom of God to give to his Church, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Divine Worſhip, which were Types and Figures and ſhaddows of what was Spiritual and Heavenly, reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chriſt</hi> who was the Subſtance; being Carnal Ordinances impoſed until the time of Goſpel Reformation, as the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> at large declares.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.19.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> received the Sign of Circumcſion a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, through which the Promiſe was made,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.13.</note> that he ſhould be the Heir of the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> received the Inſtitution of the Paſſeover, and under his Miniſtry was compleated the Law of all Ceremonial Rites, Sacrifices, Prieſthoods, Times, and Places of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; But <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> put the laſt Hand to finiſh and fix the Administration of all Typical Divine Service by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing the Courſes for the Prieſts and Levites, and Building the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the only fixed and authorized Place (in the World for Sacrifice to be offered) by God.</p>
            <p>In all which there was not any the leaſt particular of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Invention or Inſtitution;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.2.</note> for <hi>Moſes</hi> who was faithful in all the Houſe of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5.</note> made all things according to the Pattern ſhewed to him in the Mount, and did all things according to all that God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exed.</hi> 40.16.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him, ſo did he.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>David</hi> a Man after God's own Heart, and <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt of Men did not preſume to appoint any thing concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Service of God, of their own Device. The Place for the Temple was deſigned by God, and Conſecrated by Fire from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52075:10"/> Heaven; and all the Buildings and Apartments of the Temple;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cron.</hi> 28.11.12.19.</note> all the Courſes of the Prieſts and Levites withall the Veſſels of Service in the Houſe of the Lord, were according to the Pattern <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had by the Spirit, all which ſaid <hi>David,</hi> the Lord made him to underſtand in Writing by his Hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, even all the Works of that Pattern. But all theſe though of unparralel'd Magnificence and Beauty in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure; full of ſublime Wiſdom in their deſign, and of ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant Inſtruction in their uſe, were yet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.18.9.</note> as the Sripture ſaith, <hi>Weak and unprofitable could make nothing perfect.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10.</note> A yoke not able to be borne.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.7.</note> A Law faulty and decaying, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to make him perfect,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.9.</note> that did the Service as pertaining to the Conſcience,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 7.21.</note> For it was not poſſible thereby to take away ſins.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.4.</note>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the Wiſdom of God to revoke his Church from Ceremonial Ritual Service, and to prepare for the Simplicity and Liberty of the Goſpel Worſhip;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> cauſed the Glory and Excellence of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law to decay and wax old, and at laſt to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away. This was the reaſon the Structure of <hi>Zorobabels</hi> Temple was ſo ſadly unlike the Magnificence of <hi>Solomons;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.8.</note> for Silver and Gold were then as before at God's diſpoſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Temple had no Ark, nor Mercy Seat, nor <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.8.</note> All this ſignifying that Light and Perfection, Peace and Bleſſedneſs could not be manifeſt, while the firſt Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle was yet ſtanding. Therefore at laſt the Temple was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroyed not in Judgment for rejection of the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Jews,</hi> but in Mercy to the believing <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in remedy for ever againſt Ritual and Ceremonial Worſhip. For if the Law of Ceremonies when commanded and bleſſed by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52075:10"/> God were a Yoke too heavy for any Neck to bear; how dangerous then is it for any Humane Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to tempt God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10.</note> by commanding what is by God with no leſs Solemnity aboliſhed then it was before Inſtituted?</p>
            <p>Concerning which <hi>St. Chriſoſtome</hi> eligant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Diſcourſes to the Judaiſing Chiriſtians of his time;<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. Orat. prima Contra. Jud.</note> that as a Phyſitian who to prevent his Patients miſchief by unſeaſonable drinking cold water, breaks the Cup in which he would drink; ſo the moſt wiſe God to cure the zeal and dotage after antiquated Rites and Ceremonies, all fulfilled in <hi>Chriſt</hi> utterly overthrew and deſtroyed <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> which was the only place lawful by God's ſpecial appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to offer Sacrifices, and perform other Rites according to the manner and time preſcribed by God.</p>
            <p>It is alſo of ſpecial remark that <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate deſigning thereby to ruine Chriſtianity, commanded the <hi>Jews</hi> to offer Sacrifices, and ſet up the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion; they replied it was not lawful in any other Place then <hi>Jeruſalem; Julian</hi> thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not only Authorized, but furniſhed Money to reedifie the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Accordingly the <hi>Jews</hi> attempted, pulled up all the Foundations of the very ruines left by <hi>Titus,</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw, and prepared materials for a new Temple. But dreadful Fire and Tempeſt from Heaven deſtroyed thoſe preparations and diſſipated the Enterprizers of that new <hi>Babel</hi> with ſo much terror,<note place="margin">Tripart. <hi>Hiſto.</hi> Socra. <hi>Scholaſt. Lib</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</note> that never ſince was made the like attempt. Upon which event <hi>Civil</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> pronounced the fulfilling of our Lords Prediction, that of all the goodly Buildings of the Temple there ſhould not be left one Stone upon another. <hi>Moſes</hi> as a Servant was faithful in the Houſe of God; he did not detract from, nor add un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any of Gods commands; and whoever preſumed, to do either <hi>received a juſt Recompence of Reward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2.</note> how
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52075:11"/> much ſorer is the guilt to Uſurp and Invade the Authority of our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> who was faithful in his own Houſe the Church of the Living God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.22.</note> over which <hi>He is the only Lord and Lawgiver,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>James</hi> 4.12.</note> who having accompliſhed, all things prefigured by the Ceremonial Law.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 19.28.30.</note> He took it out of the way,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9 24.</note> nailing it to his Croſs. Having brought in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs;</hi> He eſtabliſhed a Spiritual Worſhip ſuch as Man performed in Paradiſe; and ſuitable to what is done in Heaven,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 4.23.24.</note> ſo neer as Humane Frailty. Such only is the true Worſhip God ſeeks and accepts.</p>
            <p>Two Sacraments, Baptiſm and the Lords Supper, and no more our Lord Inſtituted in his Church, to be Adminiſtred to all Nations, and to remain until he come to Judge all ſuch as preſume to withhold from or impoſe upon his Church pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by his Blood, any thing leſs or more then his word of command and promiſe hath ordained. Theſe are not empty ſigns, but through the Spirit,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3.</note> real effectual Exhibitions and Seals to Communicate Divine Grace. But what diſmal ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock in the Church hath Satan made by the abuſe of theſe Holy Myſteries! 'Tis the inevitable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence when once <hi>Minds are corrupted from the Simplicity that is in Chriſt,</hi> to be miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably deceived and diſturbed.</p>
            <p>Innumerable have been the Schiſms,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.</note> Perſecutions, and Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of Chriſtian Churches upon this account: St. <hi>Paul</hi> who had the Spirit of God reformed the abuſes among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> concerning the Lords Supper by reducing them to the Inſtitution of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quod volumus Sanctum eſt.</note> But proud and haughty Prelates (full of that <hi>Typhus Secularis</hi> —The old bane of the Church) have Conſecrated their own will and pleaſure to be the Standard of Divine
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52075:11"/> Service. Thence came the preſumption to deny the Cup to the Laiety,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6.</note> becauſe not Prieſts in their Stile; though in Gods account every true Chriſtian is both King and Prieſt; and by the greateſt abſurdity to Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſe the Bread into a moſt abominable Idol. An Idol of <hi>Moloch</hi> to which ſo many Thouſand Children of God have been Victimes. Thus ſtill where the Hour and Power of Darkneſs prevails, the Body of Chriſt is not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated but Crucified afreſh, and his Members torn aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and tormented.</p>
            <p>As the Sacrament of Love, ſo that of Faith and initial Life, Baptiſm hath been wretchedly abuſed by the additions of vile and nauſeous or vain and inſignificant ſigns. 'Tis ſadly a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, and God in mercy grant it may not be ſo any more, that the ſame ſigns are commanded by one Church as Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lically ſignificant, and in teſtimony of Odoration; and by another Church declared to be inſignificant,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.24.</note> and without any adorable reſpect; yet in both Churches thoſe Rites are Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Conditions of Communion though never made ſo by <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But Servants that dare to turn their Miniſtry into Dominion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31.</note> 
               <hi>and beat and kill their fellow ſervants, muſt expect their doom de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned them by the Lord when he comes to Judge the World in Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Authority of the Church is pretended for this, That Name is highly venerable therefore to abuſe it is the greater crime. 'Tis an Article of Faith to believe a Holy Catholick Church, but heinous is the offence to ſubborn the Name of the Church to deſtroy the next Article—<hi>The Communion of Saints,</hi> without which the Notion of a Church is empty and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</p>
            <p>The Holy Catholick Church is the Body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18.</note> the Spouſe of <hi>Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26.</note> 'tis the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is free,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22.</note> which is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52075:12"/> the only Mother of us all. Out of this Church there is no Salvation, for whoever is a Member of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Body,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23.</note> to ſuch and only to ſuch <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a Saviour. Of this Body every viſſible Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church is an integral Part or Member.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Viſible Church Act. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> The Articles of Religion deſcribe a viſible Church to be a Congregation of faithful Men in which the pure Word of God is Preached and the Sacraments duely Miniſtred according to Chriſts Ordinance in all thoſe things that of neceſſity are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit to the ſame.</p>
            <p>Wich ſuch a Church <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath promiſed to be alway even to the end of the World;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2.</note> the Authority with which our Lord inveſted the Chriſtian Church being the ſame as before to the <hi>Jewiſh;</hi> that unto them are committed the Oracles of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</note> that is according to his expreſs Commiſſion, the teaching to obſerve all things whatſoever our Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</p>
            <p>This is the great Charter of the Churches Liberties and Power. Here is no pretence for any Juriſdiction to make other conditions of Communion then of conſtitution.</p>
            <p>The conditions conſtitutive of a Church are ſufficient for Salvation, the End and Perfection of every true Church; therefore they are ſufficient for the Title of every Member to admiſſion and continuance in the Church.</p>
            <p>This was all was required by <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 19.31.</note> 
               <hi>whereby the Churches were ed fied walking in the fear of the Lord, and the comfort of the Holy Ghoſt, were multiplied.</hi> The firſt trouble to the Church within it ſelf, was from the atempt to ſubvert the Foundation of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity by introducing other conditions of Church Communion then <hi>Chriſt</hi> appointed,<note place="margin">Acts 15.24.</note> but that was remedied by the direction of the Holy Ghoſt in the firſt Council at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:52075:12"/>
            <p>The contrary Practice to which in after Ages hath been the great occaſion of the confuſion and ruine of moſt of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Churches, and ſtill remains (like the Womans bloody Iſſue that waſted all her ſubſtance an incurable diſeaſe. So that it may be truely affirmed, the impiety of the <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> and <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> who reckoned and practiſed the groſſeſt Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities as things indifferent, proved leſs miſcheivous to the Chriſtian World, then the rigorous exacting and impoſing in different things as neceſſary. Upon which account on one ſide ſprang Separations and Schiſms, and on the other moſt bloody and inhumane Perſecutions; for it is convenient that commands not Authoriſed by right Reaſon ſhould be enforced with rage and cruelty.</p>
            <p>The conditions therefore and Articles of Peace (as they are called) in the Church ought not to be any other then ſuch as as are neceſſary to Salvation. Becauſe the Belief and Practice of every Church moſt be as <hi>Homogeneal,</hi> as are in all Beings, Life and Operation. According to this rule of Divine Truth, the Church of <hi>England</hi> reformed it ſelf from Popery, and upon all occaſions juſtifies the Reformation: Becauſe the Union of the Catholick Church depends upon the making the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations of its Being and the grounds of its Communion adae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate. So that only theſe things which ought to be owned by all Chriſtian Societies as neceſſary to Salvation, on which the Being of the Catholick Church depends, ought to be the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conditions of Church Communion. Conſequently the proper cauſe of Schiſm, lies in tranſgreſſing thoſe Bounds, which obſerved might through Divine goodneſs conciliat the univerſal Peace of Chriſtendome. That according to the ſame Evidence by which the Reformed Churches condemn the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> for impoſing the Belief of things as neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which are not neceſſary to the Being of the Catholick Church. There ought not be impoſed conditions of Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity upon any Member of the Church, which were not ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedently
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52075:13"/> neceſſary for the Being and Unity of the Church, the later Impoſition being eventually Equivalent with the former, becauſe they exclude from the means of Salvation. 'Tis Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to mix Poyſon with the Diet of the Family, and almoſt as cruel to conſtrain the Table to any Meat or Sauce againſt which there is Antipathy Muſt he ſtarve that cannot Eat Champignons with his Capon?</p>
            <p>Poyſon and Famine determine alike. How uncharitable then are they who abhor the <hi>Roman</hi> Poyſon, yet debar thoſe of the ſame Houſhold of Faith from the Bread of Life, by the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſome unneceſſary Rites, their weakneſs (ſuppoſe;) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not digeſt, They that like Champignons may Eat as they pleaſe, but 'tis inhoſpitable and barbarous to force them upon thoſe that conceit them Toad-ſtools. It is the Peace and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of every Civil Table, to allow the indiſputable Liberty of Taſts and Appetites; and to require Uniformity in Eating and Drinking, would be moſt ſlaviſh Impoſition to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and confound Mankind. How much worſe may any preſume to diſturb the Table of the Lord, the Freedom of which as well as the bounty is the Purchaſe of his own Blood.</p>
            <p>Nor was there any ſuch cuſtome in the Church of God.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16.</note> The Primitive Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſtedfaſt in the Apoſtolical Doctrine and Practice according to which ſtanding faſt in the Liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free; only neceſſary things were commanded, things indifferent in their Nature, being as they ought, left indifferent in uſe and Practice.</p>
            <p>For it is only the Divine Prerogative; and not in the power of any Creature to change the Nature of things to be practiſed in the Worſhip of God, ſo as to require what is in it ſelf indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to be uſed neceſſarily as condition of Church Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Divine Method to reſtore and preſerve the Churches Peace is to command things neceſſary, and to leave things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to the Arbitrary deſcription of every Chriſtian to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52075:13"/> or not perform as ſhall ſeem conducible to preſent edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Timothy</hi> was voluntarily Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3.</note> in order to a preſent Service; but the ſame Apoſtle would not permit <hi>Titus</hi> to be compelled to be circumciſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.3.4.</note> becauſe it would have brought the Liberty of the Church into Bondage.</p>
            <p>After the Deceaſe of the Apoſtles, many Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, not commanded by God, crept into the Church; but they were Arbitrarily practiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertul.</hi> Lib. de Cor. Militis, <hi>c. 2.</hi> Nam ſi idco dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Coronari Lice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quia non prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat Scriptura aeque retorquebitur ideo Coronari non Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, quia Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra non jubeat.</note> not at all enjoyned, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> manifeſts and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly inſtances among many others; the ſigning the Forehead with a Croſs upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral occaſions of Civil Converſation. Theſe and others by him mentioned, ſaith, That Learned Father, were only Cuſtomary Practiſes not warranted by Scripture. But for things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Rule, ſaith he, is before; I believe (for whatſoever is not of ſaith is ſin) I muſt know what Scripture it is that commands me to obey. For,<note place="margin">—Sed quod non prohibetur ultro eſt permiſſion. Imo prohibetur quod non ultro eſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſum.</note> ſaith he, this or that is not Lawfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scripture doeth not forbid it; but that is unlawful which the Scripture doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. The Diſcourſe is directed againſt the Impoſition of any humane Rite upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienceofany Chriſtian. And the reaſon isenfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>C. 11. Ter.</hi> de Cor. mil. Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ne humanum ſacramantum Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino ſuperduci Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, &amp; in alium Dominum reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere poſt Chriſtum?</note> becauſe it is not Lawful to ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any Humane Sacrament or Ordinance upon a Divine. What havock in the Church did the breach of this Rule make? One in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance concerning <hi>Eaſter</hi> may ſerve for all.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Churches (all under the Dominion of one Imperial Crown) varied among themſelves concerning the Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Eaſter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socra.</hi> Eccleſ. Hist. <hi>Lib. 5. c. 21. Euſeb.</hi> Lib. <hi>5. c. 3.</hi>
               </note> Nevertheleſs communicated without diſcord, That
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52075:14"/> variety as ſaith <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> commending the Unity of Faith. Every Sect had ſundry and divers Rites and Ceremonies; yet therefore conceived they no worſe Opinion of others then of themſelves. To be ſhort, faith the Hiſtory, among the Cuſtoms and Obſervations of all Sects, we ſhall not find two which follow and retain one and the ſame order of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: Notwithſtanding the Cuſtomary and Arbitrary pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of ſo many various and different Rites; the Peace of the Church remained intire untill the Arrogance of <hi>Victor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> Impoſed upon the Churches concerning <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and broke the Unity of Communion. Then as the ſame Hiſtory Notes, the Commandments of God were deſpiſed, and Men eſtabliſhed Canons of their own. They made no account of the Law determined by the Apoſtles, which only preſcribed the Obſervation of things neceſſary, and raſhly urged the Practice of Decrees contrary to the Will of God, contending about Feſtivals as it were for Life and Death. It is too well known what blood and ruine this Uſurpation in the Church occaſioned in <hi>Brittain</hi> and other parts of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>In ſucceeding Ages the <hi>Latine</hi> Churches differed much in the practice of ſeveral Rites and Ceremonies,<note place="margin">Council Lat. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> yet without breach of Communion. So that when the Fourth <hi>Lateran</hi> Council made a New Cannon of <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith, <hi>viz.</hi> The Doctrine of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, another Cannon immediately Decreed, That provided their Unity of Faith were profeſſed, If in the ſame Dioceſs or City, ſeveral Perſons Obſerved divers Rites; The Biſhop was enjoyned that the Offices of Divine Service ſhould be Adminiſtred to every one according to their own various Rites.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church before the Reformation the Rites and Uſages were various: ſince the Reformation (until the late Act of Uniformity) the only condition of Communion enjoyned by Law was Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription and Aſſent, <note place="margin">13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> R. c. 12.</note> not to a Uniformity in Rites and Ceremonies, but to all the Articles of Religion,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52075:14"/> which only concern the Confeſſion of the True Chriſtian Faith, and the Doctrine of the Sacraments. This was ſufficient for any Miniſter though ordained in other Form then preſcribed by the Rubrick.</p>
            <p>The Ceremonies alſo retained in the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Stillingſt.</hi> Irenic. P. <hi>122.</hi> In compoſing our Liturgie thoſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men who did ſeek by any means to draw in others at ſuch a diſtance from their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> did never intend by what they did for that End to exclude any tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</note> ſeem not to be neceſſarily Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but rather Temporarily reſerved and recommended: for the Croſs is not enjoyed in private Baptiſm; the Reverence at the Name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> is not determined how or when to be performed. Theſe and the like are declared in the Rubrick to be indifferent in their Nature, and were ſo accounted in the firſt Practice after the Reformation, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time the Church of <hi>England</hi> flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in great Peace. The diſturbance and breach of which being occaſioned by the ſtrict Impoſition of Rites and Ceremonies in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves indifferent; the encreaſe of thoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities ſtill widening the breaches and heightning the diſturban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. How eaſie might the cure be accompliſhed, if the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice or Omiſſion of all the Rites and Ceremonies in the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, not commanded by the Word of God, were left to that indifferent Freedom preſcribed in the Seventh Cannon made 1640.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 7. 1640.</note> concerning the Situati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Communion Table; and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches there unto, and the doing Reverence and Obeyſance coming in and going out of Churches, <hi>&amp;c. viz.</hi> That the Rule of Charity preſcribed by the Apoſtle be Obſerved, which is, that they which uſe this Rite deſpiſe not them who uſe it not, and that they who uſe it not, condemn not thoſe that uſe it.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of the Church is owned and believed,<note place="margin">Art. of Relig. <hi>8.21.</hi>
               </note> becauſe it is taken out of Holy Scriptures for what is not ſo, hath neither ſtrength nor Authority though Conſtituted by any Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52075:15"/> Council whatſoever. Accordingly in Divine Worſhip Human underſtanding ought not to Contrive or Impoſe, but intirely Obſerve the abſolute and ſimple perfection of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
            <p>The departure from which,<note place="margin">Religionem Chriſtianam abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutam &amp; ſimplice Arineſti ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione confundens <hi>Am. Mar.</hi>
               </note> as was long ſince Obſerved, even by <hi>Amianus Marcellinus,</hi> proved the Confuſion of Chriſtian Religion by vain Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>It is the Command of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.4.5.8.</note> therefore no Crime in Chriſtians, not to obey nor know the voice of any but <hi>Chriſt</hi> in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,<note place="margin">Eſt in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis ſervientibus non Dominium ſed Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterium Opt at. <hi>Milevi.</hi> Lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> to whoſe Scepter only it belongs. For all in the Church by what Names or Titles ſoever dignified, are yet but Servants, now the Univerſal Property of Servants is Miniſtry not Dominion. They cannot make, Laws, they can only obey and require Obedience to the Laws of Chriſt our King and Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.9.</note> for whoſe Salvation the Church waits.</p>
            <p>The Divine Will is the only Rule and Meaſure of things; Therefore <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares to the Judaiſing Chriſtians,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Criſoſt.</hi> Ora. prima adv. Judaeos.</note> that the moſt devout Severities if not commanded by God are no better then Debaucheries. That only being pleaſing and acceptable to God which is commanded by God: And that which is moſt plauſible and venerable according to Humane Opinion, if not commanded by God, is moſt vile and impious.<note place="margin">Lord Biſhop of <hi>Hereford</hi>'s Epiſt. to a Friend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Popery.</note> Accordingly a Reverend Prelat Sums up all in this Concluſion, I will in the worſhip of God do only that which his Will tells me is acceptable to his Divine goodneſs.</p>
            <p>Therefore to ſay, Though the Rites and Ceremonies be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and inſignificant, yet when once commanded by Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, 'tis hainous to diſobey; it is a real Conviction of Sacrilegious
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52075:15"/> abuſe of Authority to enforce Humane Conſtitutions Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val with the Divine Law in Matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; which is to ſet Man's Poſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezok.</hi> 43.8.</note> by God's Poſt, againſt which Crime God denounces ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Judgment.</p>
            <p>But from what Authority doth the Command proceed? If from the the Church, the Articles of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion teach that things ordained even by Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councels as neceſſary to Salvation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Art.</hi> 20.21. 1572.</note> have neither ſtrength nor Authority, unleſs it may be declared that they be taken out of Holy Scripture. If it be replied theſe are not ordained as neceſſary to Salvation, but to Uniformity,</p>
            <p>The Anſwer is clear and certain, becauſe the Connexion between the means and the end is indiſſoluble, therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is Ordained as neceſſary to Church-Communion, the means of Salvation (unleſs Salvation may be had out of the Church) is Ordained as neceſſary to the End it ſelf; Salvation and the Command being not taken out of the Holy Scripture, is no Law, therefore there cannot be any Tranſgreſſion.</p>
            <p>But if urged as a Law Civil or Municipal, it hath no more Obligation upon Conſcience, then the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute forbiding to eat Fleſh in <hi>Lent;</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> R. c. 5.</note> which expreſly provides whoever ſhall declare it to be the Service of God ſhall be puniſhed as a ſpreader of Falſe News, that is as Guilty againſt the Law of <hi>Premunire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Civil Magiſtrate is Ordained of God, and Inveſted with the high Prerogative to be <hi>Cuſtos</hi> and <hi>vindex utriaſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Tabule;</hi> but not with any power to alter or abrogate any Command of God, or any Ordinance of Divine Worſhip, or to enjoy, any other Condition of Church Communion then is expreſſed in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>It is not in the power of any, no not by the Univerſal conſent of Mankind, ſo to change the Nature and Signification of any Acts,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52075:16"/> of Worſhip as either by applying to a Creature what is peculiar to God, or by Inſtituting any Devotion to God, not by him required.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet</hi>'s def. of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning Idolatry, <hi>&amp;c. page 259. 260.</hi>
               </note> It being (as was before Obſerved) a Principle of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Religion to Worſhip God only accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own appointment, for Worſhip not at all Commanded by God is not Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip but Fancy,<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>De Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Evang. L.</hi> 1. cap. 18.</note> and can have no Obligation upon Conſcience; which in performances of Religion is the groſſeſt Contradiction. We muſt be taught by God what is due Honour to God: For as it is <hi>Crimen laeſae Majeſtatis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hibar. <hi>De Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. Lib.</hi> 5. p. 54.</note> not only to perform Allegiance to another Perſon then the King; but to Make or Conſtitute <hi>ex proprio Motu,</hi> a Law for the Acts or Circumſtances of Allegiance to be tendred to the King, becauſe thereby is directly Invaded the Supreme Athority: So to apply Acts of Divine Worſhip to a Creature, and to addreſs to God in Worſhip by any Rite or Ceremony of Humane Invention, both include Blaſphemy, becauſe thereby is taken away from God the Peculiarity of his Dominion and Excellence whereby he is God alone. For as the Sovereign Prerogative of making Laws of Civil Government is not Transferable to any Subject, much leſs may any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture uſurp the incomunicable Attribute of Divine Auchority, to make Laws of Religious Worſhip. This happy Priviledge belongs to the Magistrate, that what is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready a Divine Law,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet</hi>'s Irenic. <hi>Page 44.</hi>
               </note> he may Enact to be a Law of the Land, and require the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of what was before in Conſcience Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, and Animadvert upon the Offenders. The Princes of the Hethen World might well be allowed to make and unmake their Religious Rites, becauſe Invented and Authoriſed only by themſelves, and thence many of them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to receive even the Flattery of their own <hi>Apotheoſis.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:52075:16"/> But every ſober Mind judges all ſuch Aſſentation to be as a great Offence to the Divine Majeſty, who will not allow the giving his Honour to another; ſo a real Contumely and mock Honour to any Prince, to Inveſt him with Divine Authority. 'Tis no leſs ſinful now by a new Mode of Deification to place the Magiſtrate in the Throne of Chriſt, who only hath Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Right to make the Laws by which Kings Reign. It is therefore worthy the Conſideration of all Chriſtian Princes, that the very making Laws for Religious matters not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God ſhakes the greateſt Prop of Thrones, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of Duty which in ſuch a Caſe hath no Obligation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.22.</note> Therefore <hi>Daniel</hi> when caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro the Lyons Den for breaking the irreverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Law of <hi>Darius;</hi> tells the King that God had delivered him from the Lyons, foraſmuch as he was Innocent before God, and had committed no offence againſt the King, which could not be true if the Decree of the King had been Lawful.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 27.6.7.8.</note> God gave to <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> abſolute Dominion over all the World, threatning Deſtruction to whatſoever Nation, would not Obey him. Notwithſtanding it was Holy and Pious not to Obey him, when his Command was otherwiſe then the Command of God. For pure and undefiled Religion, which Obliges to Obey the Magiſtrate in all matters of Civil Policy forbids Obedience in Matters of Religion not warranted by God's Word, and Commands to ſuffer rather then ſin. This, from the Apoſtles days until now, hath been the Epidemical Motive to perſecute the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe they do contrary to the Decrees of <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17.7. Gregi Nazi. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. Prima con.</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.</note> Upon which account <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſianſen</hi> objects againſt <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, the Contrivance of this Peſtilent Miſchief againſt the Chriſtians; that whereas it was the general Cuſtom (and not refuſed by Chriſtians) to perform a Civil Reverence to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52075:17"/> Statues and Images of the Emperors, upon which alſo were uſually Engraven Repreſentations of ſome Triumph or Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of the Emperor. <hi>Julian</hi> inſtead thereof, with his own Image cauſed to be Engraven the Idols he worſhiped. Thereby either to enſnare the Chriſtians into Idolatry, if they Reverenced his Image, or if they refuſed; to expoſe them for doing contrary to the Imperial Decrees generally obſerved by Chriſtians. The like Device hath been long Practiſed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force Humane Rites and Ceremonies, and ſtabliſh Hierarchich Policy in the Church, by procuring from Princes, Laws under the Specious pretence of Uniformity to enforce their Religious ſigments. By which <hi>Julian</hi> ſubtilty, the Chriſtian Churches muſt be either entangled in the Yoke of Bondage to Humane Rites and Ceremonies from which Chriſt hath made them free;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5.1.</note> or if they refuſe the Snare muſt be expoſed to ſeverities, as if the moſt heinous Malefactors.</p>
            <p>This is one of the Impious Policies propoſed to the <hi>French</hi> King to extirpate the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion in <hi>France.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> de la <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> de</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, p. 84, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.25.</note> Such crafty Policy the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> foretold would be uſed to deſtroy the Holy People, that is the Church of God. And whether managed by an Eccleſiaſtical or Lay <hi>Papacy</hi> the difference is little. How ſad a Proſpect do's Chriſtendom preſent when moſt of the Princes and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates muſt either execute or be expoſed unto the rage and cruelty of Prieſts, who have indeed that Title to the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.5.</note> for Inſtruments of Cruelty are in their Habitations. 'Tis a diſmal truth that all the Perſecutions of the Heathen Emperors cannot equal the Inhumane Barbarities &amp; innumerable Slaughters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, by thoſe that call themſelves Chriſtians, upon Chriſtians, becauſe they dare not perform any Act of Worſhip to God, not Commanded by God. For upon this Point depends the real difference between Religion and Superſtition. There ſprings
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52075:17"/> the Corruption; what ever followes is but the inlarging and deepning the ſtream of endleſs Error. So that as it was juſtly charged upon <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicero <hi>de O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi> P. 212.</note> that while his profeſſion owned a Deity, his Practice and Diſcourſe, effectually over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw Religion; becauſe he denied the rewarding and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power of God. It may be as juſtly charged upon thoſe that enjoyn Humane Rites and Ceremonies, that they open the Flood-gate of all Schiſm, and expoſe to contempt Divine Worſhip, while they talk Zealouſly for Religious Order and Uniformity. For whatſoever obtains Authority in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience muſt be received from God before it be delivered to the Church, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſeth, diſclaiming on his own behalf,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.</note> and all the Apoſtles all that Spiritual Dominion, and Authority over the Church which belongs only to God.</p>
            <p>There is not therefore any thing to be done in the Worſhip of God, which God hath not Commanded. Becauſe to every thing in every part of God's Worſhip, a Word of Command is neceſſary to be a warrant of Practice; and a Word of Promiſe for hope of acceptance, without which nothing can be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but rejection as of vain Oblations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.12, 13. <hi>For whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> Rom. 14.23.</p>
            <p>Every part of Worſhip is an Act of Obedience to the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lord of all Beings; but if not Commanded is preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to the warning, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Add thou not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Word, leaſt he reprove thee, and thou be found a Liar.</hi> Such performances have only a ſhew of Wiſdom in Will Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. but are real Uſurpations upon the Authority of Chriſt, the only Lawgiver in Religion. 'Tis Sacriledge, which in the proper Notion is to RobGod of his Honour in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Worſhip, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Thou that abhorreſt Idols, Doeſt thou commit Sacriledge?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6.</note> Every Act of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commanded Worſhip derogates from the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52075:18"/> Perfection of Chriſtianity, and the faithfulneſs of our Lord <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and conſequently prefers the Shadows of the Law, (which were compleatly Inſtituted) before the Subſtance of the Goſpel. Every Rite or Ceremony not Commanded by God, is contrary to the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, and the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Chriſtianity, wherein we are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſtand faſt;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Minia. Falix.</hi>
               </note> and as <hi>Minucius Faelix</hi> expreſſes to erect it a Trophy to God, above the Commands of all Wordly Dominion. For not only what is forbiden expreſly in the Goſpel, but what is beſide the Goſpel is unlawful. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. It prefers Humane Opinion before the Wiſdom of God, it is called, <hi>a Tempting of God,</hi> Acts 15.10. And conſequently is a ſin of preſumption. A breach of the Firſt and great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and Him only ſhalt thou ſerve;</hi> which is not performed by any uncommanded Worſhip, for the Precept is plain and Peremptory, <hi>Ye ſhall not add unto the Word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dent.</hi> 4 2.</note> 
               <hi>which I command you, neither ſhall you diminiſh ought from it, that ye may keep the Commandments of the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Will of God (to which nothing can be antecedently good) is the only Eternal Reaſon of Good and Evil; and the Declaration thereof his Word, is the only Rule to direct the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional mind, how to ſerve and worſhip God, and how to perform the Duties of Righteouſneſs and Charity to all other Beings. The Obligation and Rule of Diſtributive and Commutative Juſtice, is plainly expreſſed in the Word of God, ſo that every Common underſtanding knows the meaning of—<hi>Thou ſhalt not kill—Thou, ſhalt not ſteal;</hi> no leſs plainly and fully doth the Scripture teach all Religion, which is Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice toward God,<note place="margin">Pictas eſt Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia adverſis D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </note> whoſe ſole Prerogative it is, to teach how he will be Worſhiped. 'Tis Sacrilegious Detraction from the Infinite
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52075:18"/> Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God, to imagine the Rule of Faith and Life, needs any Infallible Interpreter, or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Legiſlation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7.</note> Therefore <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Law of the Lord is perfect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.96.</note> 
               <hi>and I have ſeen an end of all Perfection, but thy Law is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Broad.</hi> It is not ſcanty in any directions to bleſſedneſs, or the means thereof; in the Word of God, and only there may be found the ſure Rule to avoid both the confuſion of Libertiſm, and the Tyranny of pretended Eccleſiaſtical Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility and Authority. If the Golden Rule of our Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do to you, Do ye even the ſame to them;</hi> were Written (as the Emperor <hi>Severus</hi> cauſed it in his Pallace) in the Courts of Princes, it might be a happy Memorial, that as they juſtly vindicate the Invaſion of their own Royal Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and Legiſlature, their duty is to preſerve inviolate the Majeſty and Authority of God Almighty by whom Kings Reign, who is a Jealous God, and will not give his Honour to any other. The Lord Chancellor in his Speech to both Houſes of Parliament, <hi>Apr.</hi> 13. 1675. Printed by his Majeſties ſpecial Command, ſaith, <q>That Religion as it works upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; as it is an inward Principle of Divine Life, by which good Men do govern all their actions, the State hath nothing to do with it; </q>which doubtleſs ought to be underſtood agreeable to St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the Apoſtolical Power, <hi>can do nothing againſt the truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>but for the truth;</hi> that is, there is not any power under Heaven Civil or Eccleſiaſtical can lay any Obligation upon Conſcience in Matters of Religion, and a Religion, without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is no Religion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jeſuites</hi> indeed (and it well becomes their Morals) teach that their Church hath no power over Internal Actions,<note place="margin">Jeſuites <hi>Morals Page</hi> 387.</note> the evident Conſequence of which Poſition overthrows the Foundations of Religion, and Chriſtian Piety, but other Doctrine cannot be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52075:19"/> expected where Religion is only an Artificial Worſhip, and the Church only a Politick Guild or Corporation.</p>
            <p>As there is but one God from whom, and to whom is derived and directed all true Worſhip (though as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>There be many called gods, whether in Heaven or in Earth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</note> and there is <hi>the God of this World)</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26.</note> ſo there is but one Church <hi>the Mother of us all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>the Heavenly</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Which is the Piller and Ground of truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.17.</note> the Word of God which only Sanctifies Religious Commands to Oblige Conſcience. Yet there be many Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſome Heavenly, ſome Earthly: For beſide the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Pollutions of ſome Churches which render them Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues of Satan; There is alſo in ſome Churches, a mixture of Civil Policy by which the Word Church becomes a Law Term, and ſignifies a Body Politick, endowed with certain Honours, Priviledges, and Revenues by the Munificence of Kings. Such is the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, and ſuch is <hi>Eccleſia Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licana,</hi> according to the Purport of ſeveral Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,<note place="margin">26 H. 8. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> in, which reſpect it is a part of the Eſtates of the Realm.<note place="margin">24 H. 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>Lord Ch. Juſtice</hi>
               </note> But all the Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Dignities given by the Crown to the Church,<note place="margin">Cook 5. <hi>report.</hi>
               </note> as it is a Political State in the Realm, is in order to, and for the ſake of thoſe Adminiſtrations ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to its Being, as a Member of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Article</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> that is, a Congregation of Believers, in which the Word of God is pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Preached, and the Sacraments in things neceſſarily requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to the Inſtitution of <hi>Chriſt</hi> rightly Adminiſtred. It muſt be therefore altogether Irrational and Unchriſtian to ſuborn an Authority in a Political Church to ſubvert the Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Liberty of any Member of the, <hi>Catholick</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>If the Reverend Prelates of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> would govern their power according to this undeniable Rule of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52075:19"/> would notably conduce even to their own ſecurity. For if the Ceremonial Accidents in the Church were not neceſſarily impoſed, the dignified Accidents therein would be rendred more agreeable to all Chriſtians and Mankind. If Religion were cleared from Additional Superfluities, which can no otherwiſe ſecure and adorn it, then Clouds and Miſts do the Sun, the World might enjoy the deſired felicity of our Lords Kingdom, the Empire of Light and Love. Priſons, Fagots, Gibbets, would be no longer the miſerable Propagators of Faith, the Benign Influence of Princes, would not be Intercepted from their Subjects, the Obedience of Subjects would be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious, Religion (no longer ſuppoſed an Awful trick) would be embraced and obeyed in the abſolute perfection and ſimplicity of Divine truth and Goodneſs. For therein only may we find a certain Foundation for laſting Union among Chriſtians. Force and Violence may under pretence of extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating Hereſie; or exacting Uniform Decency and Order de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine in a Common Calamity and Deſtruction; by ſuch Courſe Princes may be deprived of their People; and People forced from their Dwellings into Graves or Goals or Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. But that is Deſolation not Peace. 'Tis not Union but Depopulation. No,<note place="margin">Tacit. <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſolitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem faciunt, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Apellant.</hi>
               </note> the way to find and ſtabliſh Peace is only in the way of Goſpel Truth, which gives Glory to God in the Higheſt, Peace on Earth, Good Will toward Men and among Men; From which only can be hoped a certain Foundation of laſting Union a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves. For ſuppoſe a preſent Submiſſon and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance unto the Humane Rites and Ceremonies enjoyned as Conditions of Church Communion; yet there can be no Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty ſuch Union ſhall be laſting, becauſe the Terms are Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarily alterable, and may with one breath vaniſh and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appear; to make make room poſſible for ſhaddows of another Mode but no leſs troubleſome. Hath not this been within freſh
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52075:20"/> Memorie, miſery and almoſt our ruine? But if we conſider what is our Defence againſt the Common Enemie, we may find what may be our Cement among our ſelves.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet's</hi> Rat. Acct. Page <hi>53.</hi>
               </note> Learned Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> in his Rational Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Grounds of the <hi>Proteſant</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath excellently demonſtrated. <q>That the Union of the Catholick Church depends upon the Agreement of it in making the Foundation of its Being to be the Grounds of its Communion. For the Unity being intended to preſerve the Being, there can be no reaſon given why the Bonds of Union ſhould extend beyond the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of its Being, which is the Owning things neceſſary to the Salvation of All. From whence it neceſſarily follows that whatſoever Church impoſeth the belief of other things as neceſſary to Salvation, which were not ſo Antecedently neceſſary to the Being of the Catholick Church, doth as much as in it lies break the Unity of it. And thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches who do deſire to preſerve its Unity, are bound there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by not to have Communion with it ſo long as it doth ſo. Theſe things premiſed, ſaith he, we ſhall thereby find what the neceſſary Conditions of Eccleſiaſtical Communion are, and conſequently where the proper cauſe of Schiſm Lies in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing thoſe Bounds, and what Foundations may be laid for the Peace of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Upon theſe Grounds was the Church of <hi>England</hi> Reformed from the Idolatrous Superſtition of <hi>Popery,</hi> defends it ſelf againſt their aſſaults, and thereby can only be preſerved. For the Church, which is the Houſe of the Living God, can receive no Edification but what is Homogeneal with the Foundation;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20.</note> the Doctrine of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10, 11.</note> &amp; Prophets <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> himſelf being the chief corner Stone.</p>
            <p>The Sum of all is briefly compriſed in the Words of a late Learned and Pious Divine in the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>George Lawſon</hi>'s Coment. upon the <hi>Hebr.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> N. <hi>5.</hi> Printed <hi>1662.</hi>
               </note> viz. <q>He that will
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52075:20"/> not ſerve a God, is a profane Atheiſt. He that ſerves any but the true God is an Idolater; he that ſerves the true God after his own Fanſies, and the Inventions of Man, is a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Fool. He that Inventeth Rites and Ceremonies and Modes of ſerving God, and impoſeth them on others is a preſumptuous Wretch; for as God alone doth know what kind of Worſhip and Service is fitteſt to be performed unto Him, ſo He only hath Power to Impoſe it.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:52075:21"/>
            <head>Theſe two Books are lately Printed for <hi>Nevil Simmons,</hi> at the Three Cocks at the Weſt end of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, and <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the Princes Arms in <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi>-ſtreet, <hi>1681.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CHurch-Hiſtory of the Government of Biſhops and their Councils Abbreviated. Including the chief part of the Government of Chriſtian Princes and <hi>Popes,</hi> and a true Account of the moſt troubling Controverſies and Hereſies till the Reformation. Written for the Uſe eſpecially of them: I. Who are ignorant or miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the ſtate of the Antient Churches. II. Who can not read many and great Volumes. III. Who think that the Univerſal Church muſt have one viſible Soveraign, Perſonal or Collective, Pope or General Councils. IV. Who would know whether Patriarchs, Dioceſans, and their Councils, have been, or muſt be the cure of Hereſies and Schiſms. V. Who would know the truth about the great Hereſies which have divided the Chriſtian World, eſpecially the <hi>Donatiſts, Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Arrians, Macedonians, Neſtorians, Eutychians, Monethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> &amp;c. By <hi>Richard Baxter,</hi> a hater of falſe Hiſtory. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Epiſcopacy; confuting by Scripture, Reaſon, and the Churches, Teſtimony, that ſort of <hi>Dioceſan Churches,</hi> Prelacy, and Government, which caſteth out the <hi>Primitive Church-Species, Epiſcopacy, Miniſtry,</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,</hi> and confoundeth the Chriſtian World by Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Uſurpation, Schiſm, and Perſecution. Meditated in the Year 1640. when the <hi>Et coetera</hi> Oath was impoſed. Written 1671. and caſt by. Publiſhed 1681, by the importunity of our Superiours, who demand the Reaſons of our Nonconformity. By <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:52075:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
